And what we now know is we have the
benefit of long-term longitudinal research
to
help us understand clear priorities in
educational programming for individuals
with
autism. And while there still rages a
debate about best practices for educating
children with autism, and there's a lot of
passion about one methodology versus
another, this research tells us that it's
not so much the name of the approach, but
the focus of the approach.
And the focus of the approach that really
has come to the forefront is this notion
of social competence, social communicative
competence and social emotional
competence. Why is that? Because for all
individuals, not just individuals on the
spectrum, social competence plays this
major role in our ability to form
relationships with other people. And it's
those relationships that allow us to
function happily and effectively in the
communities in which we live.
So, to be able to hold the jobs we want,
to engage in the extracurricular
activities
that we're interested in, and to basically
participate in daily life. And it's this
social communicative competence and this
ability to actively engage in our lives
that then translates into very important
long-term outcomes such as quality of life
and mental health. So, for individuals
with autism, this notion of social
communicative competence or social
emotional competence.
Becoming this key priority, we need to
understand as educators what really
underlies
those, that ability for individuals and
what are the vulnerabilities that
individuals with autism have that impact
their social communicative competence. We
know even from diagnostics, right, from
the DSM V, that social communication and
social interactive difficulties are part
and parcel of the diagnosis of individuals
with autism on the spectrum. So we need to
be able to make sure that we're
supporting those areas.
But we also need to understand the breadth
of social communicative competence and
not just focus solely on the social
communication piece of it.